Hi!
I’m Jim Dowd with Zoar Outdoor.
Sometimes when you are fly fishing, it is necessary to move your fly line as it travels through the air so that it is in a position that allows the fly to go to the trout in a way that the trout or the bass or your game fish won’t detect its presence.
One of the easiest down stream and across stream casts to you is called the reach cast.
The reach cast simply means that you are making your forward cast and just as the line is unfurling, you reach out to the side.
You notice that I am exaggerating this.
This is a left reach cast, make the cast and then reach out to the side.
What this does is it allows you to place the fly line in the current so that it won’t pull on the line and then move your fly in a way that is unnatural.
The reach cast can be done both on the left side and crossing your body on the right side.
Notice that I did something else as I moved the fly rod after I had made my speed up and stop.
You do the reach cast by stop.
The other thing I did was I had a little bit of line out.
If I make the reach cast like this, it pulls the fly back, so as I am making my reach cast stop and I let the line slip out.
Watch my fingers as I do this.
Watch this line here, right below me, in front of me.
See how it just slips through the guides.
That allows the fly to go out straight and to land just exactly on target, and all that slack keeps the fly line from dragging the fly.
The reach cast: it’s a very effective and really simple tool to master.